go
all right so everybody welcome to our
second q a with john vervecchi we're
going to be recording
uh today and we've just created a
youtube channel to host
these uh these recordings that we do for
the events that we have here
uh so please be aware that that we are
recording and
in the notes channel up up top
uh you can find a link to the to the
youtube channel so we'll try to get the
recording out for anybody who wants to
re-listen
or uh who couldn't get a chance to be
here
so thank you john uh for for being here
again we're gonna try
to do these i think every two weeks yes
please
yeah so that that's great and uh we'll
try to figure out the best times
uh i know you know we have an
international audience so we'll
we might do some experimenting to find
out the the optimal times or different
times to give people
a shot but we'll try to find out what
works for everybody but
so we'd like to shoot your questions if
you could
whoever uh asked questions last time
maybe hold back
and let some new people ask some of the
first questions
and then uh come in a bit later
uh so who has a question for for john
i do um great
right hi um so
i have watched what you've said john
about
the having mode and try and just sort of
been trying to think about
what it specifically means because i
wasn't it
didn't it was sort of a bit general and
what i've thought is perhaps that it
means
sort of keeping the self
static and trying to kind of fit the
world to one's self
so it's sort of agent-centric um
and then obviously from there i
considered that
there had to kind of be an opposite of
that where we just sort of let the world
imprint on us um i don't know if that
corresponds to the being mode or not
and then i then i thought perhaps that
sort of having both of those in a
cooperative relationship
is what would be kind of optimum
cognition
i was just wondering if that but whether
that's an accurate representation of
what you meant
and what you think about i mean it
sounds a little bit more like piagetian
assimilation and accommodation
which i do talk in a series about um
the idea that the having mode is static
um
has gotten i think i would agree with
uh because the having needs are
homeostatic needs their
needs of maintaining homeostasis so
water you have you need to have water
because uh for home
and light and it'll be a
self-terminating um
need fulfillment because you once you
achieve homeostasis you're not thirsty
anymore
um so in that sense i think
the having mode is more static um
and the being mode is definitely
developmental i wouldn't say that's the
world making an impact on you
um that's where
needs are met not by trying to achieve
or maintain or conserve a homeostatic
state
but actually needs that are met by
complexifying cognition
in some way getting in emergent
functions
and so while you definitely need if
you're not a poetic thing
to have a set of practices that are
going to maintain the internal
environment's homeostasis
and that's what the having mode is
directed towards
you also need um a set of needs
that motivate the organism to complexify
its cognition so that it can adapt
to and be ready for a much wider variety
of both social and physical environments
so for example and we tend to represent
this with
uh not with things that you consume or
control
uh but with virtues that you cultivate
so they like the example i give about
becoming more mature what we mean by
that i mean we literally mean at some
level
that you're complexifying your frontal
lobes so that you get capacities for
reflection
and self-direction and pursuing
long-term goals that are
much more adaptive to you long-term over
many
many different contexts and so
um i think in both of them
both the having mode i mean in both
you're solving problems but you're
solving a different kind of problem the
first is like i said it's a categorical
problem
of trying to control things uh whereas
the developmental
needs that you find within the being
mode are more
they're not directed at a specific
object or target
that you're trying to control or consume
they're actually directed towards
uh the complexity and uh dynamic
potential you have
for connecting to yourself to each other
in the world so that's why those needs
are much more about those connections
that establish meaning in life establish
identity did that
help yeah pretty much um just
one question to make that absolutely
clear is there such thing
as a pathology of excessive
being mode because being mode sounds
very positive when you explain it this
way
well actually i mean the the pathology
is never in any of the modes but in
modal confusion
there's two types of modal confusion um
one is
where you try to meet the being though
the being needs within the having mode
and that so to use it my example that
follows on what i just said
you know instead of complexifying your
cognition and becoming more
more mature you go out and buy a car
like you do symbolic consumption instead
but of course you can have the reverse
um you can have the reverse where you're
uh you're trying to satisfy having needs
within the being mode
um and i mean
that's not as prevalent in our culture
uh but
they we used to uh when i was growing up
and i was
i was brought up in a church right uh
there used to be certain people we would
would be sort of criticized and avoided
and that the phrase that was used was
being too heavenly minded to do any
earthly good
uh that they were always in talking
about meaning and things like this but
they they didn't actually make any
difference
in uh directing people's having needs
like making sure that people are well
fed well clothed etc
so that pathology does occur it's not as
prevalent in our culture as the other
kind of
modal confusion but there have been
times in the past
um and in certain and like i said i
experienced in my own life
where they're individuals who
misconstrue
and a particularly vicious form of modal
cons
modal confusion about this is practices
around mortification of the body
that somehow by destroying the body um
and trying to get rid of its having mode
needs
you will achieve great spiritual
perfection you can see this both within
the christian tradition
you can see it also in the buddhist
tradition where siddhartha practices
you know asceticism to the point where
his you can see his spine
from even though you're facing him from
the front he starves himself
to the edge of death and then he
realizes that this is all
actually very useless the having mode
has its place
uh and um the the thing is not to try
and crush the having mode but to
appropriately remember the being mode
to the the the answer is to not fall
into modal confusion
so i think the answer if there's two
ways in which we can be morally confused
both of them i think are disastrous for
us i highlighted the one that prom
highlights
because from thinks that our current um
normativity of the market
as sort of our de facto god tends to
create much
more uh modal confusion where people are
in in a mistaken fashion trying to
satisfy their being needs within a
having mode
but the other is completely possible and
does happen historically
thanks completely makes sense thank you
anyone else
okay so this kind of ties back to the
beverage interview um
i wasn't very happy with the way that i
dealt with my question it took me a
while to figure out why and
the conclusion i came to is that i was
trying to ask
on behalf of christians and that wasn't
working very well so
to put in my personal terms i wouldn't
put narrative into a metaphysics so i
don't have an objection there
but my question is if a narrative has a
norm of realism um and it cannot place
itself within a metaphysic
is that nor is that narrative not then a
self-undermining narrative and does that
not maybe lead to the
um post-modern skepticism towards grand
narratives
as a whole so let me
let me make sure i'm understanding your
question i you
accepted a point about trying not to put
narrative into our metaphysics
but now you're talking about
um sort of the what do they call it when
they do work on fictional entities
it's a suppositional metaphysics or
something you know that there's a
there's a a a purported realism within
fiction
and that in one sense undermines
it at least performatively because
the realism the fiction is undermined by
the fact that the very medium in which
it is found
is is not it does not have any
metaphysical grounding
and that's something that the
postmodernists have pointed out did i
get you correctly
um sort of um i would say that i don't
consider myself a realist
um so it's not so my narrative doesn't
try to
frame itself in real terms at least uh
as reel is understood you know in the in
the classical western sense
um so i i don't see a problem with the
fiction as such
what i see a problem with is if you say
the fiction must not be a fiction
and i think that's the disconnect and i
don't see if you can't put the narrative
into a metaphysic then i think that any
narrative of realism will create
absurdity i think we're agreeing
uh yeah so so i guess
the i mean maybe the maybe the
disagreement and maybe this
this would be a a very long thing i know
we've discussed this back and forth a
bit
um so if you're not a realist like
so are you are you treating like is it
an
idealistic stance you think i don't mean
in the romantic sense i mean like in
you know in the berkeley and or or or
you know fiction sense
um sort of for me it's a little bit
complicated because
i would say that that things are real
and then
nothingness is not real but you can
still speak about it
just not in real terms so
uh if a narrative
just to make sure i understand you
because something that's similar to that
is the neoplatonists
who define realness in terms of
intelligibility but the one
is beyond intelligibility and so it is
therefore beyond being
it is something like is it something
like that you're talking about
uh yes if you take being to be static
and then you're trying to talk about the
dynamic and the dynamic is beyond being
like there's a very much an attempt
within the western
uh tradition that i see that attempts to
make everything static
and if you tie that back to our
conversation about aristotle and the
dynamic telos that's exactly like it's
trying to get back at that same
problem of trying to kick the narrative
into a dynamic set
into a dynamic language that doesn't
depend upon realism and it's the attempt
to staticify everything
and make it um discrete and like a
self-contained entity
that that fractures the whole thing and
that's the that's fundamentally what
realism attempts to do
at least within the western
understanding of realism
yeah well well classical realism i mean
you have
very many modified forms of realism like
putnam
sort of integrated uh pragmatic realism
um but let's play in that in the field
in which you've set things up
um so i think i agree with you there too
and i think that overlaps with the
argument i have
uh made that the the
uh for all my love of plato the but
especially plato
um the equation of most real with
perfection
and static completion and that that is
our model for sacredness and then of
course that ramifies through all of our
normative
judgments i think that's a fundamental
mistake i think that's a very
fundamental mistake
um and i would come very very close to
what you've said there but i would make
a distinction because you draw a
distinction between sacredness and
the sacred and i would say it's
appropriate to speak of this sacred
aesthetic
but you want sacredness to be dynamic
and you you want a balance of both
i kind of see you as a reactionary in
that regard and the thing is about
reactionaries is that they have to go
too far in order to be effective so it's
not really a criticism of you
but it's like we gotta we gotta get both
oh okay uh well yeah um
yeah okay i i think maybe i have a sense
of
what you're talking about um that there
might be
some aspect in which the eternal um
is grounding space and time and
therefore uh
shouldn't be thought of in sort of
dynamical terms
i think that's also something i would
plausibly consider
um yeah okay so very i mean this is
getting a little bit esoteric but i
would say that the static is more like
what is of origin and then the dynamic
is more of like what is of destiny and
like
the now is kind of the meeting of origin
and destiny and so you've got
you it's like you were speaking about
modal confusion
the issue is about like the the having
mode is like the static
mode and the being mode is like the in
your language is the dynamic mode
i would say that the being is static and
the becoming is dynamic but the idea is
to shift the narrative off of a norm of
uh realism in the static sense so that
it can
it can operate in the no thingness that
that dynamic no thickness which
which speaks towards the renewing
sacredness if you if
i don't know if that lands no that
landed well i like that
that was good
okay so um would you agree then that
the christians and the realists have a
real problem in that they can't make
sense of a narrative that isn't within a
metaphysic
when you are supposing realism is a norm
and do you see a way around that if you
are
if you're trying to to to craft your
your framework
in terms of realism
um so you you're asking me to speak on
behalf of the christians now
well no i i i would say that you try to
your
your framework attempts to create to to
hold realism as a norm
would you agree with that well yeah
because but because i think it is a norm
but there's uh you already said you
you you accept the normativity of
realness
and that's typically what i'm talking
about i want to be able to make
comparative judgments
and so some things are more real than
others
yeah the the thing is that um i was
speaking with um jared morningstar on
this
like i think there might be a disconnect
between the western and eastern
notions of realism and i kind of get the
impression
like uh nishitani his idea of real
is thingness and nothingness together
yeah and
right so i think that you're trying to
do that as well
but that that seems to me to be
incompatible with the western notion of
real which holds the realness
i do disagree with you i mean in
platonus and proclass
the one is both no thingness and
ultimately
uh real right like i think there's a
similarity
in major traditions in the west um i
think you're right that when that gets
taken out when that neoplatonism gets
taken up into christianity
it that inner that that that keeping of
the two together
uh becomes very very problematic uh for
for well yeah i think this uh um if i'm
right the council of nicaea had a
similar kind of conflict over
um the meaning of hypostasis because i
had a different meaning in greek and and
like it meant sub substance to the to
the latin if i remember correctly
yeah substance not as stuff but in the
real aristotelian senses stops
substance when it's supposed to mean the
underlying principle right
right so i i think i i where
i'm trying to i think you're trying to
get at the underlying principle notion
of realness and i'm focusing more on the
substance notion of realness when i'm
trying to speak about this like okay
so yeah yeah but but part of my argument
is
i think there has been uh the underlying
principle notion
of realness yeah i i i'm not i'm not
uh criticizing here i'm just trying to
speak to the miscommunication because
what i think is going on with the
christians is that they might be hearing
the substantive side of it when you're
talking about the underlying reality
side of it yeah
that's astute i agree with that i and
you know i've been
i'm i'm gonna have a conversation with
paul about this and
i mean even even the translation of
hypostasis into person and then taking
person not to be sort of the same as an
aristotelian substance but making it
personal like us
there's there's been a sort of series of
moves in there that i think we need to
go back and unpack more
uh history right exactly exactly that's
that's right
where i'm because the whole narrative
thing seems to be tied into this idea
but what it
what it means to be a person and how the
personal
ties in with all of these other concepts
and i think that the learning crisis
to a large degree has been uh
like this whole language has fractured
in on itself and we can't make sense of
ourselves and because of that we can't
really
create a language to connect to other
people properly anymore
yeah i think that's right and i've been
trying i don't know
how successful i've been trying like
when i've been having discussions with
paul and mary and jp
and and then people on the other side
like rave kelly
about is it possible to separate you
know
sacredness or the you know god as the
symbol for that
uh from the notion of the personal to
try and get away from that whole
but there's there's a lot of these these
moves that we've just
we've agreed on have happened they're
locked so tightly it's
hard to get them to articulate in the in
both the sense of speak and open up
spaces between the parts
uh so you can get clear about uh you
know
your own tradition might not even be
committing you to this
in the sense that you know before that
collapse happened
there were many alternative ways even i
think within
the west like we've explored for for um
doing uh relating to
sacredness more appropriately i
i don't i i i like i take your point
very well though that one of the things
that locks
the two are locked together right the
collapse of hypostasis
into a personal being is locked into
trying desperately to see the universe
as a narrative
really really a narrative yes i think
that's right
and i'm not quite sure um
how to unfold that
for people that's very very tricky
so i have a a another question from
uh antalesh in the in the voice chat
so so he asks i have a question about
the use of heuristics as a guide for
truth
if heuristics bias us how can we use
principles like
parsimony occam's razor etc wouldn't
parsimony be a value that biased you
away from truth
insofar as there are no objective values
um so saying there's no objective values
first of all let's work backwards as
equivocal that could mean the universe
doesn't possess
value or it could mean that those values
do not act as proper norms upon
a practice which i so while i agree with
the first
there's no objective values written in
sort of the physics of the universe
i think norms especially when they're
acting like virtual engines
really do regulate our you know
practices that we want to engage in so
um parsimony
is an interesting one uh because the
problem with it
is it's and this is one of the problems
with occam's razor
is people think they know what they're
talking about
uh but actually trying to specify
take the design stance try to give a
machine
you know the principle of parsing money
what does that mean for it you know
don't multiply entities
beyond you know this is typical don't
use more entities than you need to
explain something
while entities are not they don't come
pre-packaged and individuated
i mean when i say that evolution is
caused by natural selection is natural
selection one entity
how do you count it um no it's a whole
raft of things that have to come
together
so was that a simple thing that darwin
did in comparison to paley
or a more complex thing the problem was
with with simplicity the is that the
only formal
version that i i find sort of
interesting or convincing
uh simplicity is literally
computationally intractable
um so all we ever do is use heuristic
approximations for it
so i'm going to collapse parsimony for
that reason back into
like any of the other heuristics that we
use
and like and we have to use those
heuristics
because we do not pre-specify a bias
where
where where we look for information we
are going to hit culminator
explosion and commit cognitive suicide
um the trick
is not to try and escape from heuristics
and this is what liu and i argued in the
paper
no sorry tim and uh
and little crap and blake richards and i
argued in the relevance realization
papers
you want to get sets of complementary
heuristics
that can act as checks and balances on
each other
because you can't really be free from
heuristics
so um what i don't think
heuristics condemn us to falsity
and i don't think the fact that we're
using norms
and there aren't norms right written
into the fabrics of physics
also uh undermines our use of norms
they're you know practices and forms of
interactions
are regulated and constituted uh by the
virtual engines govern them
and norms are typically ways of trying
to state virtues
state way state ways in which you create
the conditions
in which a practice will exist you know
and so this is the notion of
constitutive norms
as opposed to objective values you know
if i want to play
you know football i have to follow the
rules not because the rules are
written into physics but because if i
don't follow the rules i can't
do the thing i want to do which is to
play football in a similar way
you know if i want to try and gain
knowledge
learn and solve problems i have to use
heuristics now i can use them better
or worse and that's the choice that's up
to me so
i think there's a constitutive necessity
to cause
of there's a constitutive necessity
cognitive agents if you want to play the
game of cognitive agency
there are norms that you need in order
to engage in the practice
then you may and then you may ask well
what's the ultimate value of the
practice well
solving problems is that
all of your cognitive agency depends um
and i don't think you can live in
existence in which you say well what i'm
going to do is i'm not going to solve
problems anymore
that doesn't seem to me to be any way
viable so the move i made in the answer
was i tried to show you that
parsimony just becomes another heuristic
the heuristic are constitutive norms not
objective values written into the
physics
that's fine that's how most practices
operate
and then within that what we should
think about is not just using heuristics
individually
but how we can constellate them together
so we get the most self-corrective
process
possible
great uh any any other i hope i hope
that answers your question
on tulisia any other uh other questions
i heard some people speak up before
well i have a question but i'm not quite
sure
how to phrase it it's been uh
beating me up a little lately they've
started opening up
in our state more businesses for
economic
purposes so people can get out and about
and i just had the feeling like oh my
gosh this
new emerging paradigm that we've all
hoped for is like
that was it it's like we're not going
back to the old and
so um i heard uh
john you say uh fake it till you make it
you were talking to
jordan this was about five months ago
before a lot of this
started and and so uh
faking it until we make it uh being
emerged
in practices is i believe what you were
speaking of so that's kind of a law of
attraction
principle and so i'm just thinking how
can we
uh at this point with this emerging
paradigm
get on board where we're uh co-creating
it
imagining it focusing on what
and you know i understand a paradigm you
can recreate in your own being
i'm thinking you know globally much like
what you two were talking about
and so um you know first you decide what
you want and we've kind of
done that you have this amazing platform
here now
on discord and all of your wonderful
offerings so you know we kind of know
where we want to go but
then the second part it seems of
creating a paradigm
is identifying the belief that supports
the reality emerging reality and that's
where
you know i there are so many different
beliefs and they're all
you know wonderful and they all go
together uh
but i've noticed people change their
beliefs you know even if i look back a
year
we keep our core values and certain
beliefs of course
but you know to integrate beliefs
and and it was seeming like you were not
wanting to
to go there it's like we'll start with
the practices we'll do the
horizontal uh you know and then let the
rest emerge and and i
i think that's what has to happen the
higher
view viewpoint the story what's our
story what's our narrative the divine
narrative
you know that kind of emerges on its own
but yet uh you know are there certain
steps we can take to be doing the most
we can
uh in this co-creation it seems to me
that sometimes uh
we have to be selective uh and not just
objective in what we're what we're
looking at we can choose what we want to
look at
uh you know that's how things have
always
been created by thought first so
you know this is your field so how do we
uh work this
shift that's going on right now with
with what
uh of our capacities that we have we can
use
um so so that was a lot i'm trying to
make sure that i parse it correctly um
so
you what your question could mean you
know i think
it means both what what should i be
doing individually
or what should we be doing collectively
uh to try
yeah to try and sort of take take
advantage of this
kairos this opportunity to shift things
um so
one of the things that i mean
you well you already know part of my
answer because you alluded to it
i think we need to set up communities of
practices and we need to set up
communities of discourse here's
here's a community of discourse but
notice that it's not really
tied to a community of practice other
than discourse
now brett doing some amazing things
about trying to
link you to communities of practices uh
so for example i'm doing the
uh the live stream meditation class um
right now and what's up and that's a
community of practice obviously i'm
i'm teaching them things but that's
we're not there primarily to discuss
we're there to learn a practice learn it
together and then
when that whatever the discussion that
emerges it's discussion around
the practice and so what we need to
think about
and this is part of what jordan hall and
i are trying to talk about is
how do we get these various communities
communities of
different communities of discourse
different communities of practice
um to start um talking uh
to each other and practicing with each
other now that's already happening i
mean i
i'm not taking on some titanic
responsibility i just want to facilitate
something that's already happening
more and more people are trying to to
say
well what would it be like if we
you know people who belonged to a
community of discourse al
also belonged to a community of practice
and what if people who were both
talking and practicing also started to
generate you know a community of
generation
uh where they're starting to uh generate
uh ideas
put things out to the the wider society
because you obviously know what model
i'm thinking here i'm trying to think
about
all the ways in which religions sort of
went from being nascent clusters of
small group movements into something
that became
more comprehensive and so that's the
kind of strategy i think we have to
pursue and then a way
you know a way to do that your the
individual role in that
is if you want to partake in you know uh
founding
uh different communities and then
forming a small world network between
them because i think that
we should use small world network
structures not hierarchical structures
we should organize them
the way the brain organizes its
processing
but what you should think and
and what we should all think myself
included is
well what are the requisite sets of
virtues where by virtue i mean
you know skills states of mind states of
character
um what are the requisite virtues that i
would need
in order to help found and connect
these kinds of communities together and
then start cultivating them
and and i and i don't say that
dismissively or trivially i know that
that's a
that's a huge thing to put on people
um and but
so i i i'm not
i'm not trying to be in any way you know
authoritative
but what i'm trying to say is that's
what i think is needed that idea of
trying to create these meta communities
um
and then trying to individually
cultivate the skills
that are needed in order to create these
meta communities
well this is probably a good place to
plug that a few of us it's been a small
group but
on as as you john are doing your
meditation class on youtube a few of us
have been meeting here on discord
where we listen on youtube and mute and
then afterwards you know chat a little
bit about
our experience excellent excellent and i
mean if that you know and so if that if
that group becomes a bridging group
you know bridging between ideas is one
thing bridging between groups is is
is another thing and if this group that
you're talking about brett you know if
it becomes a bridging group between
uh the you know the meditation and
contemplation saying that
and then this larger discord group here
that would be the kind of thing i'm
exactly talking about
and of course everyone is welcome so the
more the merrier
to join us uh it's uh monday to friday
at 9
30 eastern as long as john's doing it
and maybe
uh i i know john you're in your your
last week of your course i'm not sure
what you're
i don't know just just uh well here's a
good time to talk about that now we're
going to go forward
so i'm going to teach i'm going to
there's some things i'm going to
continue to teach
from this tradition a little bit more
advanced um and then we're probably
going to
write so um what we're going to do is
because we're getting a lot of requests
for people who are just finding out
about it
we're going to alternate so we'll go a
week where we have a dharma day a
teaching day on monday
and then the rest of the week is set and
then we'll have we'll have a week that's
just sitting there after
so there'll only be a dharma uh once
every two weeks and all
so there'll be about three or four more
dharma sessions
doing a little so that'll take us a
couple months in and then by that time
um we're probably going to shift to a
format
where we have something like what i call
the wisdom sangha
uh which i've run that in person before
for about five years
and so i've got some sense of how that
would look going forward but i need to
work with omar a lot more because
it's going to be handled through of
course a different medium
et cetera but that's sort of the
overarching plan so this is not coming
to an end anytime soon
great so everyone please please join us
uh weekdays 9 30 for for that uh here in
the discord
anyone else have a have a question
uh hi hello hi
uh nice to be able to speak with you
like this
um it's a little off topic but
i'm just very curious you mentioned in
your meditation
course that you have uh
shiatsu uh therapy
as practice and i was curious if you can
explain a little about that
that leads to their work
oh so i mean that was
very much uh you know me trying to
recapitulate
uh recapture i should have said
recapture
um the you know the an ancient ecology
of practices
so uh so i had a
you know this is all around cultivating
uh the virtue of mindfulness which i do
not think
is uh well i shouldn't be so strongly
i'll just say what i think is better
i think what is best is to have to have
a meditative practice
a meditative sitting practice a
contemplative sitting practice
you need some moving mindfulness
practice like tai chi chuan
um chi kung things like that and then
you need
not only is it a moving mindfulness
practice but
it's interpersonal and it it is healing
and that's what that's what shiatsu was
so i actually
about training in zen shiatsu um which
is
um you know it's it's in the family of
things like acupuncture and acupressure
it's like acupressure uh but it's
rhythmic and you trace out entire lines
upon
uh the body and what what's that what
that
is good for is it's good for dealing
with things that are
uh psychosomatic and psychogenic uh
that and therefore fall between the
cracks of of sort of western therapy
because it's not you know physical
health or mental health that you're
addressing
and it's not trauma or infection
it's more how people you know might be
that the the mind-body relationship is
sort of getting out of sync for them in
particular ways
and that might express itself
psychosomatically uh
in a physical way or it might just be
you know
like i said a psychogenic thing uh
and so what you're doing is it's really
interesting because
like i said you you have to be in a
mindful state yourself
and you do this rhythmic it's almost
like the person's body becomes
and i don't mean this in any graphic or
sexual way the person's body becomes
like a musical instrument and then
you're sort of tracing patterns
on it and the idea is this is a very
you know interactional and mimetic way
in which people sort of
catch your mindfulness catch it
and but they're also put into a deeply
receptive state
um and then they get sort of ins that
mindfulness is sort of
tracing out uh patterns of nerve
stimulation
which sort of help people i think
you know reconnect um
uh areas of the brain um and areas of
the nervous system
together in sort of new patterns and
that
helps uh people very very very
considerably
i mean i i'm very critical of people who
take a magical attitude towards this and
that
they're moving around unseen energy or
stuff like that i think there's a
completely naturalistic
and important uh explanation of chi or
ki
and i'm going to be publishing a paper
on that hopefully this year
it's it's pretty much written and it's
about to be submitted
um so and and then and make panacea
claims about shiatsu like it will cure
cancer or
uh you know help you if you've got the
measles or something
no it won't but it does do well
for like i say that inter-categorical
place where people are
disordered and not at ease diseased
um in their minds and bodies and the
relationship between mind and body
it's very powerful and so when you see
when you sort of can share mindfulness
in that
procedural and perspectival way um it's
it really um it's really interesting
what happens there's some
evidence i've seen um sort of eeg and
stuff like that when people are
uh when a therapist is giving shiatsu
you can see the brain wave patterns
become much more concordant
with each other and we know that this
starts to happen anyways when people are
doing distributed cognition
so i think a healing fact is really
important for showing you
the potential of mindfulness to be
something at work within distributed
cognition
and also sort of its capacity
to orient you towards healing other
people
which is is an important way of deeply
remembering
um our interconnectedness with other
people
so sorry
i hope that helped definitely thank you
my mother is a shiatsu therapist
and i guess i also
peer away from the people who
do it religiously but i also believe
there is
truth to it and that was very helpful
and i'm very
looking forward to the paper oh thank
you
thank you
good question can i jump in or line
yep go ahead
yeah go go ahead
so john um i've been i've been following
your project and listening to your
videos and um
recently i've started reading um into
some into
post-modern theology i wonder if
there's some overlap between your
project and
what's going on there um you can
set this up a bit um as i understand it
there are sort of
two main movements
one movement is um radical orthodoxy and
they
have a similar genealogy um
sort of tell the story of
um the the decline into nihilism
starting with
with scotus and probably discard us
and their sort of um way of addressing
that is to
break down the dualism between nature
and grace and
ontology of participation yeah
should be people like um milbank and
others
and then there's a another movement
within
post-modern theology which includes
people like john caputo
yeah yes i've been influenced by darada
and tilly who i i know you're also a fan
of
and i he also speaks of a religion
without a religion and
notice you've got similar terminology so
hearing if if you've been influenced by
any of those thinkers
or yeah engage with their work
yeah um so
john caputo has had a considerable
influence on me
um his book on the mystical element in
heidegger thought
was very formative for me and so i know
that branch
of post-modern theology uh very
well um i've read a lot of derega
studied it taking courses on it etc and
so
and i've seen some of the interaction uh
between derek and sort of negative
theology
and jean-luc marion's work uh you know
um
god without being so i'm aware of that
string milbank i don't know
i could this is you're the second person
in a week
that has recommended that uh that name
to me
um and so on no bank i i just have a
very
very minimal passing knowledge i see him
cited in some of the other books
um i've been reading especially books
around uh the mystical
origins of orthodox christianity
and you know i see marian being very
very deeply influenced
uh by neoplatonism
and so all of those things and as is
caputo
um i've also read uh mark taylor
who is also a postmodern theologian
historian
of religion and his book after god
um has had just a huge impact on me as
well
so in terms of the the influence some of
the strands the ones that i've mentioned
um especially uh mark taylor and
john cabuto have definitely had a huge
impact on my thinking
yeah that's that's helpful um i i
mentioned
um i don't know how well this overlaps
with your project but this
is is in radical orthodoxy's discussion
on
the ontology of participation and uh
to break down the distinction between
nature and grace i wonder if that sort
of um
acts at all with uh what we were talking
about with the actual age religion
yeah yeah you cut out for a sec was the
person you referred to was that bill
bank is
that what you just described the central
bank project yes
yeah so what what book would you
recommend as
you know um i i'm philosophically
educated so i don't need sort of a
an introduction but what's a good book
by his to
you know get it get it to the core of
of his work yeah i'm the wrong person to
ask i'm i mean
i i've just been reading an introductory
book
myself so i just i just noticed
something else between what you're up to
and i
i wanted to put that out there and see
what you're
so yeah i mean and this goes towards
something that i've said
to paul mandeckley and jonathan pajot
you know i don't have a
foreclosure argument it may be that
christianity
in you know in the ways you're
describing here but also in ways that i
think have to deal with the narrative
issue and the narrative metaphysics that
were talked about earlier
um is it possible that christianity
might reformulate itself and break
the stranglehold that the axial age
mythos and grammar have on our thinking
and afford us a way back into right
relationship with being and a response
to nihilism it's possible and when
you know when i when i hear about this
the kind of stuff you're talking about
that you know that's why i want to keep
keep the discussion going
um i still have the criticisms and
you've heard them mentioned earlier
uh but it's i think it's also
trying to predict what a religion will
do and how it will go is a
really really tricky thing to do i
always make i always state that
how it seems to me because that's i i
don't think i have any right to claim
beyond that
how it seems to me is that christianity
will not be able to reformulate itself
to address these problems
um and but i also always acknowledge
that that is not a
foreclosure argument i'm really really
hesitant
to people who make sort of foreclosure
arguments with
and uh so there that's my answer to that
i think so i'll i'll leave this um leave
the questions to someone else but
yeah thanks you're welcome
i think we just have what a few minutes
left uh
are there any other questions that
anyone has
well i've got another question but
sorry go ahead um i i had a question
about
um if there is a dynamical relationship
between the agent arena
system can this be data
can this be simulated through data or
what kind of data input
we can ever have that's right
and that's a really good question uh so
i'm working on stuff with somebody right
now
so obviously you know that's a that's a
broad sort of philosophical construct
and
what you have to do is you have to via
you know good theory
you have to specify into particular more
specific
uh constructs and entities and so one of
the ways
we're trying to do that one thing i want
to do is
i want to study uh uh conversational
patterns
uh and see and and so what happens in
things like circling is people get into
like a collective flow state and while
it's self-organizing
um it's it's generally not
it's generally not self-perpetuating um
at least initially or
or maybe again this is an empirical
hypothesis so i'm just
i'm just stating suspicions here what i
want to what i want to study is this
when people are getting into distributed
flow because they've got a particular
network
does that then lead them to modify the
parameters of the interaction
so that they keep refining flow together
so so they put parameters on the state
space to create an
attractor that keeps bringing them into
configurations of interaction
that maintains the distributed flow
state and that's something i'm
i'm first of all trying to work out the
theory of the map and then see if we
see how we can go about trying to
actually measure that
in action so that's the kind of thing i
think that that was in no way exhausted
you understand that please
that is an example of you could take the
general principle specify it in one way
and then do an empirical investigation
you'd need to do tons of those
right and then once all the varied set
try
and not like after you've done a lot of
top downing into various
specifications then gather them together
and do the inference to the best
explanation bottom up
and try and extract from all of it more
general principles
that are nevertheless built on specific
empirically tractable constructs
so that's the kind of thing i think you
should do okay
thank you you're welcome
we have a question from student of
movement in the in the
text chat uh one of the issues you bring
up is with regard to our current
scientific worldview
no longer being compatible with axial
age two worlds mythology
one thing barred one thing bard proposes
is a move is a move towards monistic
versions of religion
i see the later developments many of the
traditions move towards a type of monism
non-dualism to resolve this issue
whether it's in buddhism with the form
with the move from early forms to
mahayana
form is emptiness emptiness is for or
samsung
or samsara is nirvana et cetera
or my understanding of contemplative
mystical christianity
example jesus pointing out how heaven is
present within
essentially they move from two worlds
being places to psychological states
comments or thoughts on this approach so
i agree with everything until the very
last statement
um they don't move to i wouldn't say
psychological states
um i that's one of my criticisms of
young i think they move to a
constellation of
cognitive states and existential modes
and also
patterns of distributed cognition and
cultural systems
um so so um
so what i'm saying is the locus for
where it's found
the ontology of monism is not
it's not the same as saying everything
is just a psychological state
so the primary argument
i think for why that happens is found in
spinoza
um spinoza's argument is if we think
sort of a tilikean idea that we're
trying to get
some relationship to what's ultimate
i'll try and use that as a neutral term
though attilic does
and then spinoza's basic argument is
if you have any kind of dualism you
haven't you haven't achieved ultimacy
uh because the each one limits the other
and the principle that unites them and
affords their common interaction
is actually um the ultimate principle so
that kind of arguments for monism i
think are very important
and so that's a conceptual argument for
ultimacy and monism and then we have
you know a a a similar
argument uh for physicalism uh within
the fall
within the philosophical foundations of
uh of current science
and i do think that both
of those sort of uh if you'll allow me
to
because i'm running out of time to speak
very a little a little looser
you know the movement of monism within
sort of the existential project of
coming into right relationship
uh with uh ultimacy so within
you know with not not within modernism
the movement towards modernism
within sort of a religious arena uh as
we try to get into a right relationship
with ultimacy
and then the movement uh within
um our scientific metaphysics to get
um an integrated account and this is
the argument for this is that um
realness
is dependent upon judgments of realness
at least i'll try to
not speak so metaphysically uh judgments
of realness are dependent upon judgments
of intelligibility
and judgments of intelligibility need a
need common principles of
intelligibility need an integrated
coherent account etc
and so whenever you're positing two
worlds you're actually undermining
intelligibility
and so you get an epistemological
argument within
uh science for why we should move to
monism and then you've got
an an existential argument within
religion why we should move to modernism
and the thing that needs to happen and
spinoza is an exemplar of somebody who
does it
his book is called the ethics which is
all about our aspiration to right
relationship
with what's ultimate and blessedness but
he's writing it in
a logical mathematical form emulating
and i think mastering the cartesian
science of his time
he's right in the heart of the
scientific revolution and spinoza was
trying to show
how those two things uh could be folded
together
and so i think um
sorry this sounds pretentious i aspire
to seeing myself in his lineage
i didn't get to talk about him very much
in the series because
he's kind he was kind of actually
orthogonal to the history unfortunately
but for me you know i've read the ha
this is a bit of a pun
i've read the ethics religiously like
every day
lectio divina read on it study it
reflect on it read commentaries go back
and back again
until you start to see the world the way
spinoza saw it until you actually get
scanci intuitiva
not just reading about it and so i see
myself in that lineage with spinoza
of trying to i take very seriously these
right these existential
and epistemological arguments for
modernism and then
how do we realize this how do we realize
this
and that's very much i think the way we
have to go
so although i don't have a foreclosure
argument
on christianity and i still stand by
that or buddhism
i'll still stand by that i think that i
think dualism is doomed
i think dualism all the dualisms the
mind-body dualism supernatural natural
i think all of those dualisms are
ultimately doomed i had to rush through
those two arguments the existential
and the convergence between the
existential and the epistemological
but i was trying to give you a gesture
as to why i think the dualisms are
doomed
it sounds like a good title for a book
and do elizabeth doomed
so so i think i think you're out of time
uh
though thank you so much this was great
the hour went by very
very quickly uh thank you everyone who
asked questions don't worry in two weeks
we will be doing
another another one of these so you'll
have you'll have your chance to ask
ask all those questions then so thank
you very much john we really appreciate
it
and appreciate your time and i think
this was great thank you so much
the questions and the interaction i'm
really impressed
again as i was last time with the
quality of these questions
and the willingness of people to enter
into you know
a cooperative dialogue about it and back
and forth and really try to unpack
things together
i really enjoyed my time so thank you
everyone thank you very much thank you
okay take care we'll talk to you later
okay bye bye bye
all right great thanks everyone you guys
don't have to go you can continue
uh chatting of course and thanks tyler
for
uh for recording today appreciate it